this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
see radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society I believe software
Magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
this is Philip Winston with Bastion
Gruber Bastion has more than 10 years of
experience developing software much of
it as a freelancer he was part of the
official rust async working group and
founded the rust Intel Berlin meetup
group today we will discuss his new book
rust web development
thanks for joining us Bastian yeah thank
you for having me I'll just say a few
words about rust to set the context the
rest programming languages has roots
going back to 2006 and the 1.0 release
was in 2015. Rust is a systems
programming language and is considered a
safe alternative to C and C plus without
compromising performance
the stack Overflow developer survey has
named Russ the most loved programming
language every year since 2016.
an example usage is AWS uses rust for
its firecracker system which Powers AWS
Lambda its function as a service
offering
and in 2022 rust became the third
programming language used in the Linux
kernel after Assembly Language NC
so Bastion there are many popular
languages and Frameworks for web
programming why do we need another one
that's an excellent question and I get
asked this a lot in my experience like
Russ is the first real different
language in the other languages you
could say you move from python or to
node.js you move even to go
but they sort of have the same feel and
there's nothing really radical new with
rust you have the type system and the
compiler and I think that you also have
a whole group of people who come from
like a ruby and like node.js which
helped design the language so it feels
like a new Like A New Beginning it feels
like a very new and fun language to work
with and it's not just a new syntax it's
a new thinking
new compiler yeah it's new it's
radically new okay so you mentioned a
few but what does Ross bring to the
table relative to web programming that
you feel makes it a viable Contender I
think you first have to
step back and say like why would I write
it in Rust because I think like the Crux
about it is it's not really batteries
included when it comes to web
programming or like to create like web
services
but a few but it has enough to get
started so I think when people try to
approach it they look at which packages
can I like use if I come from python or
from go how does it look like in Rust
and I think that's the wrong approach
like I think it helps a lot to look at a
type system and the compiler and what
this means for the longevity of a
software project it makes it more robust
and more easy to work with
and then you can think about like the
rust
compiler make sure that your black
memory is thread safe without a runtime
which both helps in like writing
applications for the web
because the asynchronous way of writing
code is still quite hard sometimes and
rust makes it safe and then after you've
compiled your application or like your
web server it runs very efficient and
with not a lot of resources required so
it's both safe to write to to like
maintain but then in production you save
costs and you can be sort of sure it's
safe throughout its lifetime
so I can imagine two paths to using rest
for web programming one is learning rust
for other applications maybe getting
good at the language and then deciding
to use it for web programming and the
other would be to Jump Right In and
learn rust and web programming at the
same time and that might your book might
bear on on that path but can you comment
on those two paths how viable each of
them is so the thing with um Russ like
for our for all its advantages you need
a sort of a base the base is not a lot
it can take a month or two three months
maybe read the first four five six
chapters of the Rust book so if you want
to jump straight into web programming
you will see that it will struggle more
than if you would pick another framework
or like language then this is you have
to get used to how the rust compiler
thinks and wants to guide you so if you
jump straight in you will get frustrated
but if your mindset is I have to learn
part of the language at least to know
why I have to write us like a certain
way then you will have more success if
you're super used to maybe C plus plus
if you're used to three four different
languages you might succeed but if you
just have like one stack in your past I
would recommend to learn the language
first write a CLI application first and
then jump into web programming
and the Rust book I think you mentioned
is the Russ programming language by
Steve klabnick and Carol Nichols right
like you can purchase this book but it's
also open source and free to read in the
browser
so reflect the standard reference on
Rust
so are there web programming
environments or situations or
applications where you think rust is not
the right choice for web it's really
hard because there might be something
I've never touched or heard of if I
think back in my career now and I think
back okay I used here node I use Java I
used partly go I don't see a reason why
I wouldn't use rust for these use cases
it can be that you need to prototype
really fast you need on Monday and you
know by Friday you need something
working to show to an investor or to
like a customer and it just has to show
a few things
then like rust if you are not as
experienced might not be the right
choice because the compiler wants to
make sure your program runs safe and if
you prototype you know the pitfalls and
you don't care
if it's safe since this
application will never see the light of
production so if you really want to
prototype fast and there are not two
three years into the language it's not
the right choice for you
I can see that I can't remember if you
covered this in the book but how did you
personally start using rust and then how
did you personally get involved in Rust
for web programming so I was on my I was
a contractor I had a no chess project
and around the corner was like in Berlin
there was the Mozilla headquarters in
like in Berlin and they had like a
Meetup called like the rust programming
language and then I Googled and thought
hey this sounds interesting it seems
like assistance programming language and
I was sort of done with no chairs
because I've done 10 15 different
projects I saw all the pain I didn't see
how node can solve it so I thought I
need a new language to solve these
problems and back then it was Prior rust
1.0 so it was I think 2014. so like I've
tried it I thought I don't understand
anything about it I dropped it again and
then in I think in 2017 or 18 there was
a JavaScript conference in Barcelona and
Steve klapnick he presented like the
language in a little booth and he also
said there's the first rust Meetup in
Barcelona feel free to join so I joined
there I saw the language and like what
fascinated me was the people who joined
there were open-minded
they were open to fail it was not this
strict like I joined a few gold meetups
and I felt like a bit out of place and
with rust I just felt home personally so
I thought hey that's great I want to
also start a Meetup in Berlin about this
where people can share their thoughts
about the language and this is where I
thought I first want to start a Meetup
see which people this language attracts
and maybe this is something for me and
after starting the Meetup I thought yes
I think I want to pick up the language
so I wrote a few blog posts I was on
paternity leave back then and I saw I
want to move from node to rust so I dig
deeper into how to write a web service
in Rust so like I blocked a lot and then
I got my first like rust chops and from
then
I'm in love like with the language
great okay we're gonna go through a few
features of Russ this is very much a
subset that are covered in your book and
even a subset of that but we want to
give a flavor for what rough specific
features and how it impacts web
programming I want to refer to two
previous episodes for more details on
Rust itself there was episode 279 with
Florian gilter on Rust and I guess he's
a core rust programmer and there was
episode 490 Tim McNamara on Rust the
second one was 2021 the first one I
think was 2017 and we already mentioned
the Rust book so here's a few features I
just wanted to kind of get your read on
so one is is one of the Hallmark
features which is performance what
enables Russ to be as performant as the
fastest languages
in like in my read I'm not a compiler
engineer but the compiler like what like
what transforms your like arrest code to
like a binary and like machine code is
the compiler there is no like runtime
attached so like once your code is
compiled and in an asynchronous way like
you can think about like a state machine
your
asynchronous functions will be
transformed into like a state machine
and the rust compiler makes sure that
the memory you used and you want to like
write to is always safe and thread safe
so after you've done the compilation
process there's no overhead attached
like in Java like in node.js black and
go so this makes it very like efficient
during the runtime
because it doesn't need this garbage or
like this active garbage collection
yeah so one of the other features I was
going to ask about is ownership which I
think it relates to the lack of garbage
collection ownership is not a term I've
heard in other languages but can you
talk a little bit about how that impacts
your sort of day-to-day thinking with
the language
this is a topic many new rust developers
struggle with and I think even if you go
on and do more complex applications this
will have an impact on how you write
your code and how to think about the
code and this is a caveat of rust but
also its greatest feature it basically
says that not more than one
process or active part of the
application can write to like a memory
space so like you can have like multiple
reads but just one
right so if you pass a variable by value
to another function this function now
owns this space in a memory and if you
want to pass it multiple times the
different functions you have to think
about how would I do this so I can make
sure that I adhere to this ownership
principle that just one function can
actually manipulate the memory so it's
I'm thinking about this is where the
performance comes in and the no active
runtime comes in because the compiler
makes sure that not two processes at the
same kind can manipulate the space and
memory but therefore you have to think a
little bit about it the compiler is
going to help you and show you how to do
it in a different way
but this has an impact on your
architecture of your application
I think we alluded to it but let's talk
directly about safety a little bit I
think people that maybe have never
programmed in CRC plus plus don't fully
understand just how unsafe those
languages can be and I think it relates
to like what do we call a crash in a
language and in C and C plus plus a
crash can be the entire application goes
away or it does something unexpected it
writes to memory which gets written to
disk and there's garbage it really can
be sort of a catastrophic crash wherein
safer languages you expect
things can still go wrong but maybe
they'll be a an exception that you could
handle or maybe rust has its own term I
guess so can you talk just a little bit
about safety and what that means so in
Rust it's not possible to have sort of
like a note pointer you always have
your return like a result type or an
option type which can either be
true false or there is something or this
like nothing and if your function is
returning let's say you want to write or
you want to open like a file and this
function returns like the status of this
operation you can return a result like
which says yes this was successful or no
I couldn't actually write to this file
and then the other parts of the
applications Who call these functions
have to always deal with these both
cases so it's not possible and there's a
caveat you can obviously say
I always just cover the the success part
and don't really handle the not success
part nicely and then you have like a
runtime problem but it will never write
into like a memory space you're not
allowed to write
so like the architecture of like the
types is made so you can always handle
the not successful case and the rest
compiler itself make sure that you don't
write in any other user space
memory from other applications
so these are like the safety rails like
which rust provides let's talk a little
about the type system and then we'll get
into tooling and then Frameworks so okay
the first element of the type system I
wanted to talk about are structs so
structs in Rust you can say it's a class
or an object which defines like its
members so you can have a struct which
is an animal or a dog and it has certain
attributes
name and also so like
I'm all it's like member types and then
in Rust you take a second step and
implement this struct where in this
Implement block of this struct you will
Define the functions for destruct so
you define your objects and it's like
Members First and then if you want to
attach certain functions to this object
you have an implementation block which
is called an impul and then the struct
name and then you have for example like
a new function where in Rust there's no
such concept as a Constructor but you
can define a function called new and
once you call it you return an
instantiated type of this struct back to
the caller
how about generics the syntax looks a
little bit or a lot like Java and
c-sharp how are generics used in Rust
so the power of generics is that you
like a term called trait
bounding where you can say you don't
really know which actual type you pass
to this function so instead of saying
this is an end or this is a string you
can say this is a or b or c and then you
have a where block where you can say
this type I don't know like what it
actually is but it has to implement
certain Behavior so if you say I don't
know if it's a string or a number but
this generic has to have the ability to
print its contacts or its contents to
the console or like to form it into a
string
so now if you call this function and you
say I pass like whatever but I have to
make sure to implement this one function
to this type to be able to pass it down
to the function but it's a powerful way
of saying I'm not restricting myself to
a specific type because your application
can grow but I limit like what I can
pass down to with um certain traits and
traits in Rust are Behavior like like a
struct can implement the behavior
barking and sleeping
but also other maybe like a cat can do
the same or a giraffe and once you write
this function you don't really say I
can't just pass a dog down you say I
pass a generic a and this a has to
implement a function called barking and
a function called sleeping and then I'm
fine that was going to be my last topic
was traits so that's a good summary so
let's get into talking about tooling one
of the things people really seem to like
about rest is the tooling I'm just going
to go through five tools and just kind
of give us a sense for what they do
maybe with respect to web programming or
maybe in general we're not going to go
into detail but let's just talk about
these so the first one is rust up and I
gather this installs the compiler yeah
so this like lets you update
like the rust compiler so if a new Black
Rust version is being released and this
is done every six weeks you do like rest
up update and then you can fetch the
latest like rust version and install it
and you can specify and specify which
version you want to work with you might
have a project where you log in the
version like maybe from like last year
because you it like it's not safe for
you yet to upgrade to the latest or you
don't want to make sure like it's up to
date so like with also like the rest up
it's basically your like version manager
of the rust compiler okay and how about
cargo I think that's the package manager
can you just kind of say what cargo is
used for yeah so cargo lets you create a
new project build a new project at the
dependencies to your project so cargo is
basically your tool you will see the
most on your command line with cargo new
and then the project name you create a
new project like with the scaffold of a
new like rust project
and you can with cargo add and then the
dependency name you add a new package
which updates your dependency file and
adds the
dependency to your project you can also
have different
build steps so you can have a cargo
build and this builds like a development
like version of your application but you
can also have a cargo built there's Dash
release and then this builds a smaller
more yeah like smaller more optimized
binary for deployment the next one is
rust C I gather this is the compiler do
you ever call Rusty directly or do you
call Cargo only I haven't experienced
that as scenario where I would use rust
C by hand
so I always and you would also always
probably just interact with the cargo I
can't think about an education where you
might use rust C directly
and one of the features of Russ C are
extensive error messages I remember in
the book you did a nice job of showing
someone make a change it produced an
error you'd explain the error and
explain how to fix the air I thought
that was really helpful can you explain
a little bit about these error messages
and sort of how they direct you towards
possible fixes so in the beginning I and
we talked about was you should learn
like a basic set of rust and then you
have the ownership principle which can
be a bit challenging to learn but the
compiler if you make a mistake it can
help you direct and like what you should
do instead and this is not always the
right thing it suggests but in ninety
percent of the time and in the beginning
of your journey it's almost close to a
hundred percent of the time will tell
you what to do instead so if you don't
adhere to the ownership principle it
will tell you like what to do so you
comply to the ownership principle for
example and that's also the hard part if
you come from a scripting language
you're used to debugging printing out
stuff on your console and then trying to
fix them in Rust
you will always face the compiler
because it makes sure that your rust
code is safe and correct so you will
have to get used to lots of compiler
messages if you compile you fix them and
once it's done you can be sure wow now
it's finally done and I can actually run
my binary and this is a bit of a
different mindset from other languages
where you can like run your binary or
your script
quite soon but it can fail and you don't
know like where it fails but the rust
compiler will tell you every aspect what
you have to fix until it's finally able
to compile and this will stay like with
you in your rust Journey so the
suggestion is to get used to and
befriend the compiler see the compiler
as your peer programming buddy which is
also nice because if you're quite new to
the language you don't know don't always
have to go to a forum or to stack
Overflow you can trust the compiler to
learn from it will teach you how to
write good rust code and if I remember
it's actually showing you where in the
line the the error was not just oh yeah
like it shows you for example hey this
variable is moved here and please add
this function here so it will fix the
problem
for you so like it shows your like your
failure and then it has an info section
where it suggests
it's a better way of solving this
problem great the fourth tool I have
written down is clippy I can't really
remember what this one does so clippy is
one step up from the rust compiler
clippy is sort of right idiomatic rust
code it's a tool like it was not part of
cargo in the beginning and now it's part
of it so there are certain rules like in
JavaScript it would call be like linting
so you can run it through your code and
it will say hey
there's a more rusty version of writing
this part of the code or you can even
say I want you to notify me if I forgot
to write comments for this structure for
this function so or
like right hey you didn't return a
proper
result type for this function so it
makes sure that your code is up to the
highest standards and you define of How
High your standards should be based on
like a config file and a different type
of rules
you want to have
okay the last one I have listed is looks
like rust format rust fmt I know there's
a go format that's super well adhered to
in the go Community I don't know if this
is similar how widespread is is the use
of rust format I think pretty widespread
I've seen a few projects now where
people so then like the rest format
needs a config file and that is like
like a same set of like rules as maybe
clippy has
but people sometimes forget to use it or
don't care like what I like for example
it's able to group your Imports for like
a file like it sorts them alphabetically
it makes sure to group them or it can
even
like Nest them
nicer so it formats your code to a
certain set of Standards which makes it
easy if you work in a larger team you
don't always have to comment on hey
please write this in two lines or please
re-order your Imports you just run or
like your in a team make sure that you
all like the same type of rules you
write it in a config file and then in
each commit you just make sure
that you run it once and then it's done
so it's making sure your rest programs
look neat and tidy I've done python
development with and without a formatter
and I definitely prefer having the
formatter in there it just eliminates a
lot of conversations and it just gets
things like you say looking very
readable
so that was rust features and tooling
let's talk about Frameworks so web
programming in any language tends to
involve Frameworks because there's a lot
about web programming that's similar
from Project to project and you don't
want to have to implement everything
from scratch so I'm not sure I totally
understood again all of the roles of the
Frameworks but let's talk about warp if
you think that's a good starting point
in terms of what does it actually do and
maybe what the other options were
besides warp today so warp is a web
framework if you come from a different
environment I think that you would and
this is why I wrote In the book as well
I tend to start from the bottom up to
see why rust is different but if you
start from the top there's like a super
small easy to use web framework with
like it doesn't come with all the
battery is included I've used it in the
past if you want to write a simpler
microservice which you don't want to
have a lot of things included like you
want to be small and Tiny and quite fast
so
it's like warp is built on the Tokyo
stack and to understand like the rust
ecosystem like web Frameworks you have
to understand that like rust doesn't
come with an hdp server or it even
doesn't come with an abstraction for
HTTP because it tries to be like a
systems programming language it wants to
be as small as possible it decided to
not to implement an abstraction for hdp
so you need the ecosystem to help you
out with writing like a web application
and for this and even to implement
asynchronous code functions so like warp
is built on sort of like the Tokyo stack
so if you go one level down from a web
framework you need an HTTP server which
can run and accept hdp requests or TCP
requests and then it transforms it to
hdp Black messages and like warp is
built on top of hyper which is an HTTP
server implementation in Rust
and for it to work asynchronously and
then we go like one level down you need
a run time and like node.js you have V8
in go you have their own goal like run
time and then rust there's no runtime
included and the runtime means some form
of threats or threading or how to make
sure to not to block if your web server
gets one request that it blocks the
other 10 000 like it might get at the
same time so you need a way of telling
the processor let's work on this if you
have time and I save the work in some
way and you tell me once you have time
again to make work on this and then I
pass it on to you and once you're done
please notify me and then I can do my
part as well and in Rust the standard
run time for this is Tokyo which
implements this asynchronous thinking
like mindset on top of the rust language
and there are certain tools built on
this Tokyo runtime like which is hyper
as the HTTP server and then the S warp
as the web framework so like whenever
you use a web framework in Rust you
always also have to include which
runtime you want to use
it's not as easy well it's I think still
pretty simple to have a second
dependency to your web framework and
this will be most of the time Tokyo as
the runtime great some other Frameworks
I think were tactics web rocket and axum
are those strictly peers of warp or they
just one-to-one Replacements or are they
different
all together
so with actix I think it's a quite
popular framework and this is a very
much batteries included type of
framework if you want to start a complex
web application and you know you need
authentication you need all the safety
black meshes you know you will need
you might tend to use actex because
there's a lot of bus around it there's a
large community around it many people
are using it so it's a safe pattern not
to write everything by hand but you can
depend on act decks to already have
something for you with rocket I think
the development like when the epitome
pause lately but I'm not so up to date
it's also very much a batteries included
framework but it uses macros quite a lot
and macros is a feature in the rust
programming language which you annotate
a piece of code and the compiler
will transform this piece of code with
whatever it's in the macro so like the
macro takes your piece of code and will
transform it and there are not many
rules what a macro can or cannot do and
so there's a lot of like magic behind
the scenes which you either like it or
you don't
and then there's X um
which feels a bit like in between warp
and tactics it's more
I wouldn't say easier to use but it's
more from a mindset if you come from
like node.js you might find it's easier
to think and read about it so it's an
in-between choice if you're not too
afraid
to
yeah to like write like a middleware
yourself or if you're not too afraid or
like experienced enough to do a few
things yourself then axum is a perfect
choice with
big enough but not too big to include
too much Magic
so the book uses warp is that a
reasonable decision for production or
was it chosen mostly for the teaching
aspect so I personally used it in
production the book started with warp
and exome wasn't out yet
I didn't want to choose rocket or actex
because of the teaching part of the book
because I think it has too much included
and I want to be as close just to like
rest and the concept as a possible and
don't want to teach too much about the
web framework because it can change and
then the book has to change in half a
year again I would maybe choose Axiom
now and axum came out after I was six
chapters in I talked to the maintenance
of Excellence at hey how long do you
think it will be until this is final and
then it was clear that I'm not gonna
rewrite half of the book now just to use
a different web framework I'm thinking
about updating it or do like a web
series of how I go through the book and
update it to Exum but I would say that
that I would use XM now for the book
but warp is perfectly fine for a
production environment you just have to
know that you have to do a lot yourself
if you want to use it for a complex
application if you just have a smaller
microservices which itself for example
fetches a few external resources and
power system and gives them back like
warp is perfect for this
okay that was pretty good overview of
Frameworks now let's talk about
essentially making our first web server
I guess walking through the steps
obviously the book is going to have a
lot more detail and a lot more code but
just kind of hinting at what we're doing
here so I guess the first step might be
just setting up a web server with warp
that serves static Pages maybe or what
would be the very first or just serves
the hello world from the code or
something is that pretty simple to do
so the first step as I mentioned is you
need to think about the runtime you need
to think about
how or like which piece of
code can handle my my asynchronous code
so you would Mark your main thanks
um function in this example
you put on top of it like in a lineup of
the runtime you're using
like with a hash and just a syntax like
which is like use like it looks like a
macro or it is a macro and then you
would choose Tokyo for it
so you mark your main function as say
I'm using the Tokyo runtime so in a sub
subsequent process of the application I
can write asynchronous code
so you would include Tokyo and a warp
framework to your dependencies
and then yeah you start or like with
warp you start a server and
like what warp is doing as a testing
like it has like the filter concept so
each incoming hdp request
can get sent through a certain amount of
filters and the filters will check is it
a request I can parse so with warp you
for example can say this incomingrequest
dot get
and then you write the path you expect
the get request is for so if you have
get requested slash hello
but you expect in your path filter slash
hello world the filter would not be
triggered so then it would say no I've
expected this at slash hello the HTTP
request has the path slash hello world I
don't do much like with it I will
pass on this request so like you have to
make sure that you
add certain filters for your path for
your parameters
and then you can add filters like what
you want to do with it I think you
started talking about route handling
that was going to be my next question so
the route I guess is like a string from
the client with words string separated
by slashes and then optionally at the
end you have a query string which is the
question mark sort of value equals so
can you talk a little bit about how the
route Handler deals with Dynamic paths
or or query strings or anything
so the one important part about this
filter system is always you first have
to tell like warp what to look for in
this certain filter so like one route is
a combination of the filters and they
are added like with an and keyword so
you have to say
if it's a put like a get or like a post
or something and then you say which path
is this put for for example and then for
this path
you basically say like the slashes and
the Heart path like the not or like the
static part of the address and you can
say slash questions slash users like
which is like a hard path
and then you have like a parameter
filter for it as well so if you add this
like with a DOT end after the hard path
you can say I'm expecting like a
parameter
so for example if you want to update a
certain question and you expect the path
has an ID you will say after a question
or after the static path you edit dot
end
and then you say this has to be like a
parameter
and you can give it like a type for your
application too so you can say I want to
parse this parameter as a string or as a
number for example and then you close it
with a end and then path end so if you
now forget to add the parameter in your
request this filter will not be
triggered like that's the important part
and then it says no like I've expected
at this static path
like with a parameter if I don't get a
parameter
this filter is not triggered and then
you can write a recover function for all
like the requests which were not caught
by the filters
and the query parameters that gets
converted to a hash map Etc so you can
dictate
for like warp or for your route Handler
so in the path in like the parameters
part it will convert this parameter to a
type and pass it as this type to your
route Handler so if you say I'm
expecting a hash map or a string or
something else
this filter will try to convert this
parameter in the path to this type and
pass it as this type to the route
Handler
so we started off by talking about a web
server which generally is going to be
returning HTML you have another chapter
in the book I think focused on rest apis
what are some differences there and I
think part of that section talks a lot
about types and creating your own types
so as like with rust being a type or
like a strictly type language
you have to before you can work or if
you get a request into your like web
server and you expect in the body some
form of Json if you want to work with
this
you have to tell your like web server
like what's the type I'm getting from
this request
you can just work it as like a byte
stream you can try to convert this whole
thing just into like a string like a
byte string but you can also say this is
a Json and it has to look like a struct
then we talked about structs in the
beginning and there's a neat little tool
called survey which can automatically
deserialize and serialize for example
Json to this obstruct so if you want in
the book for example add a new question
to your database and just add this
question as a Json on this HTTP request
you can tell in your rust code now that
please transform this Json to this
struct and this is done in one line
and you can annotate or you have to
annotate your abstract like with a macro
from this tool called survey
and then your compiler automatically
knows and tries to convert this Json
you're getting to this type and if there
is a mismatch it says hey this ID you
told me that's a number but it's
actually a string
I fail
so this gives you already uh after the
request comes in some hard
struck like some hard types to work with
and with these you can
have in the route Handler after the
filters are done you can say I'm
expecting for this route Handler in the
parameter a type question and the type
is your struct and then you can work
automatically like with this
struct in your like rust code so this
transformation from struct to and from
Json is beautifully done because now you
can also compose a new struct and just
return it in warp and Survey makes
automatically sure that this will be
transformed into like a proper Json and
this is all done just in one line so
this makes it really beautiful and
really safe to work in in a web
environment
for an API in Rust okay yeah I can see
the difference between sort of picking
through the Json field by field
potentially finding or potentially not
finding something you need versus
upfront converting it to a type and then
you know at that point that it has
everything that seems like a nice way to
go
in the rest API section you did talk a
little bit about thread safety I don't
think we can get into detail but I just
wanted to mention this RC and Arc
template functions and
just what do people need to know about
them if they're going to go go learn
about them later
so next to the borrowed Checker which
you need to get used to when writing in
Rust another concept or like another
maybe a barrier is that we have to dig a
little bit deeper
because rust doesn't have a runtime you
have to think about
what does it mean to that different
processes and threads have access to the
same data if you have an in memory
storage
you have to think that like multiple
threats want to write to the same memory
space when you run like a web server
so you have to think about how do I pass
data
and I want to make sure that just one
active function or process is able to
write to this like memory space and in
like rust you usually do two things here
so you would use and here comes like the
threat safety and like the borrowing at
the same time because now it's a bit
complicated to know when should rust
drop a value if you have like a local
storage and you pass it on to like a
function and then yeah like rust things
okay like after this is done I can drop
it because no other function is gonna
use it now but in an asynchronous way
you might have
hundreds of thousands of
um spin-up threads or like green threads
which use the same like value so you use
a concept called an arc which is which M
saves the amount of
functions currently holding this value
then you can clone it so
if you for example
have an in memory storage like with all
of your questions for this application
and you pass it to 10 different like
route handlers you would put this in
memory storage behind an arc and then
you clone this Arc which means you
duplicate it but for an arc it just
increases like encounter and says I have
10 active
functions currently like using this
variable so please compile it don't drop
it and after each of like the functions
are done like it a decrements like the
pointer or I like the counter and if the
counter is at zero the compiler knows
now like no one is using this anymore I
can drop it
so now you solve the problem with how to
multiply in an asynchronous environment
like a memory address and pass it to the
different
proud handlers now you still need to
solve how can I make sure that actually
just one function at a time is is
altering this memory space and for this
you usually have like a read write log
or you have a mutex
so inside this Arc you also pack in a
read write lock or like a mutex
so if you have a route Handler it gets
this Arc of this like memory storage and
then it's trying to request the lock
from the read write log like it says I
and like I request a lock because I want
to alter this data and then this black
abstraction will make sure that actually
just one function at the same time is
altering this data and if two will
request like a right lock
it will make sure that just one of them
gets it and the other one has to wait
until it's free again so this is why you
oftentimes see in this asynchronous
environments this combination of Arc and
read write lock or new text
and then your actual data you pass
around
yeah that's a good example where in the
book you have to pause and go pretty
deep on some Rust Concepts to explain
that part of the programming but I think
that's actually a good way to learn it
when you're motivated for a specific use
so we have a web server delivering HTML
and maybe we have a a web service
delivering API results in Json now
another piece is we need to chain and
call into someone else's API and is
there anything to say about that that's
different I guess in that case you still
are using maybe do you make structs for
the the API you're calling into is that
how it works yeah so for the API calls
you can also use another crate which in
the rust world is called request like
it's a popular grade for this and it's
like along the same lines where if you
fetch a third party service let's say
like a Weather Service and you
want to use this black weather data and
you expect a Json back the beautiful
part about rust is now that some of
these apis can be quite verbose and you
might get an object back about the city
and the latitude and the weather for
each minute and for each hour maybe but
you're actually just interested in the
city name and for this
our like the weather data so in Rust and
with m30 like with like the serialized
and the deserialize like macro like this
one line on top of it you don't need to
type out the full response you can just
say this struct let's call it weather
just has a name and a temperature and a
date
and then it's perfectly fine to parse
this incoming Json to this one struct
and it will just take
those fields out you put in destruct and
all the maybe this incoming Json has a
hundred Fields but you just want three
of them you just Define the three you
want in destruct
and then it parses them down just to
this one three and the rest will just be
neglected so that's a nice way of not to
having a too large
or like two large objects in your code
base and two verbose objects you can
just work with the data you want and
need
all right one of the other topics in the
API section was databases but we're
going to skip over that here but it was
nice to read about starting with an
in-memory database and then using I
think it was postgres and there was
quite a few examples and information
there about that
so let's suppose we've got our web
service implemented there's a couple
things listed I think under cleaning up
your code one of them was the module
system and then logging and tracing and
debugging what can you say about the
module system
related to web programming or just in
general
I think there's like nothing special
about it in the rust it's just a way of
grouping certain functionalities
together and then rest it's called like
a module so if you start your
application and you see
this sort of pieces of code belong
together and this shouldn't be in the
main folder you can create for example
like a routes of a folder where for each
endpoint you compose your routes and
even maybe have your route handlers
there and then you could create a
different folder for it called like
routes you would add a mod.rs file to it
and this is sort of your starting point
into this folder and in this mod.rs file
you write out
the file names in this folder so if this
folder has
getquestions.rs get answers dot RS you
would write in the mod file pop
get questions pop get answers so then
other parts of the code can use these
pieces of code in this module in Main
you would then say like use and then the
folder name and then the name of the
module you specified in the mod.rs file
so it's just a neat way of separating
out your code which you just
yeah cleaning up I guess
for a web API
the different access points I guess or
the different routes nicely or can
nicely correspond to modules now how
about logging and tracing I'm trying to
remember were those crates
were those third-party utilities or were
they built in
so in like rust world and on
asynchronous Rust world
there is a famous like lock crate which
sort of like works as a facade pattern
so the lock crate will give you the lock
levels as a macro and then you can use
these for example info warning in your
code but the actual implementation of
this logging function nullity is done by
another crate
but this second crate is using the lock
crate sfsart and providing the actual
functionality behind it so if you ever
want to change your logging crate you
can change it but the facade keeps it so
you can use the same like lines of code
and you don't have to change it you can
just switch out your blogging crate
without affecting your code base now in
an asynchronous environment
um blocking can get messy because it's
not really clear because different
tasks on the runtime will finish at
different times and will make work on
edit at different times so your locks
might be out of sync or they appear to
be at the same timestamp
and then it's hard to say which route
Handler actually locked this part and
also in the Tokyo ecosystem there is a
crate called tracing which allows to
annotate asynchronous functions
and opens so-called spans like a span of
time so it's clear which route Handler
or like which thread
this log message is for or from so if
you operate in an asynchronous
environment you always have to think
that you can't control when or how your
functions making progress and 10 things
can happen at the same time or like
appear to be at the same time so you
have to think that your logging might
not be as clear in this environment
therefore you have this crate called
tracing which adds this few pieces of
functionality which can create a span of
time and then it makes it a bit more
clear where this log is from from which
route Handler or from which asynchronous
function
let's talk a little more about bringing
things into production and then we'll
start wrapping up
you have a section on authentication and
accounts I don't want to go through that
in detail but
is there anything to mention with
authentication is I guess there's
another crate maybe that handles that so
it depends like if you it depends on the
web framework and that's a good example
like with warp you have to sync it for
yourself
inactics I think there are a few options
like you can take off the shelf and
implement it and with Warp you have to
think about it how like would I do this
there are some crates but I found it
like it's
it depends on the environment but it's
easy enough to actually do it yourself
because you have expected in a header
some form of authentication token like
whatever plug you use and then in the
book I just use like a different
encryption algorithm and therefore I use
like a library like which like encrypts
this data so I can send it out to the
client but the book shows of how to do
it by hand and even if you might not do
it in a different environment I think
it's helpful to know how an
authentication actually has to work on a
base level and from then on there are
different crates you can use for
different types of environment I think
the book also makes clear that this
topic is quite hard to cover in just one
book I think that Manning just has an
extra book on authentication just in a
general and as we all like know it's
like a very degree critical thing so
this was the reason why I wanted to do
it by hand to show how to do it by foot
so that if you need help or if you want
to expand you know how and why and where
to look for it okay something else
covered was different environments like
debug and release compiling and also
running inside Docker images but we're
gonna skip over those I just wanted to
touch on testing though before we start
wrapping up is there some I think there
might have been something built in to
rust or cargo for unit testing or what's
built in there and what do you have to
add for testing
so like Russ comes with a test macro and
like a few function called assert equal
or a sort like not equal or like a basic
set of
functionality to write
like unit tests so you can use for
example the test Macro for functions so
you annotate a function like with test
and then in your normal
production Black Rust file you can just
add a few tests test functions there but
you can also have a test folder called
tests where you write
your tests in there and if you run on
the command line cargo test it looks for
all these functions which are annotated
like with test and runs them so this is
a like a nice way of a built in and it
has enough to write your
unit tests for if you go into
integration tests and stuff I think it
depends on the flavor of how you want to
use them in the book I explain of how
you add
like a terminology called channels to
your like web server so you can start
as server like the production server in
your test environment with certain
parameters and then you can use a
channel to send up one like message like
to shut it down again if a test fails or
if all tests are done and it's called
like a One-Shot Channel and I think that
Axiom has it actually built in like
which you can use
let's start wrapping up what features in
rust or any of the Frameworks are you
looking forward to seeing in 2023 is
there anything on the horizon that would
make
web programming easier or anything
you're looking forward to I think like
it made me hopeful and you mentioned
this in the beginning like the
firecracker yeah like written in Rust
and because like so many web services
interface with AWS for example
that there's more coming from this
Direction I hear from a lot of node and
goal programmers that they miss crates
or they think oh like why should I do
this by hand I want uh like a third
party to do this for me so I hope there
will be new releases and a more push
into yeah like more like rust flavored
third party interfaces I guess this is
like a I'm gonna look most most forward
to
so the book and this conversation we've
been talking about rust on the back end
are you familiar with efforts to run it
on the front end and that historically
the front end is Javascript but now with
wasm I guess there are ways to run
compiled languages is this something the
rust Community is working towards or
have you any familiarity with it I think
there are two interesting topics around
this like the one thing which is more
like in the blockchain like world where
people run their like rust code in like
a Vasan Block in like a virtual
environment but also I was in touch like
with a company and they do heavy
computations and it's quite expensive
to spin this up on AWS and to tear it
down again they were thinking of like
moving this to the edge so like to run
these types of computations in the
browser so they looked into shipping
this pieces of like rust code in like a
awesome blob and then
the client like itself can do the
computations in the browser so I think
this is very very interesting where you
can package up your rust code and you
ship it to a browser I think that the
docker Creator said that if likewassem
like would be out there by the time he
wrote Docker then he wouldn't have done
it because this is actually a they are
like a great way of
doing these types of things so
I didn't dig too deep into it yet but
from like the use cases I've seen is
very very interesting what can you say
about the rust Community or the rust web
Community how would someone best get
involved or get started and I'll put
links to anything in the show notes and
I'll also mention I'll put links to all
of these libraries because some of them
are spelled kind of funny I'll put them
all in the show Notes too but how about
Community is there any Central Gathering
Point people should know about or how do
they get involved so I think there are
like multiple if you like my first
attempt would also like would always be
first look for a Meetup near you or like
look for like a virtual Meetup in your
time zone because this is a great way to
actually hear people from different
companies talking about like what they
are doing and then you can chat with
real people about your questions if you
for example in in in like Europe yes the
rustlands like Meetup it's like virtual
you can get up early and like attend it
in the states and then the for the more
technical questions there is the rust
sulip server which is more like around
the actual language progression they are
like the working groups
Gathering there and talking about the
next steps in each of these environments
but there's also the rust Discord
Channel which has different I guess
rooms to take us to discuss certain
things like there's a great
beginner room like you can ask certain
questions and the help is always like
nice and fast and then each grade or
ecosystem like we talked a lot about the
Tokyo ecosystem has its own Discord
Channel where you would find hyper warp
Axiom and Tokyo so if you struggle with
understanding certain Concepts you can
go there and most of the time there like
the core maintainers of this crate will
help answer you the questions and in
generally it's like the nicest
environment I've worked with sort of I'm
used to JavaScript and JavaScript is
quite an open Community but in Rust you
have this
sort of solid knowledge of people but
they always try to help out so I would
just jump fearlessly into these
different Discord servers or onto like
the meetups and they are all super nice
and open to the newcomers
great I think that brings a full circle
to how you got involved in Rust in the
first place how can listeners learn more
about you or the book there's a website
called rustweb development.com in one
word I try to or I publish to blog posts
in the last week I try to be more active
there I try to publish blog posts there
of how to write or like rewrite certain
chapters in the book from warp to axum
they are the links I just like mentioned
on the front page
so this is the Hub or like the starting
Hub to get in touch I'm on Twitter and
there's the Twitter link I'm on yeah
like Mastodon there too and if you want
to get in touch via email you can reach
out to for each at me.com great I will
put all that in the show notes
thanks for your time today Bastian I
enjoyed reading the book and enjoyed
talking to you yeah thank you so much
for having me
this has been Philip Winston for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
[Music]
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
Channel at SC radio dot slack.com you
can also email us at team sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign